#### PERSONAL INFORMATION

# Rehana Abdulber Shemsu



- 🔰 184048, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia
- +251973748794
- x rehusmail@gmail.com

LinkedIn Rehana's Linkedin GitHub Rehana's Github Twitter Rehana's Tweet

Gender Female | Date of birth 03/02/1991 | Nationality Ethiopian

# PERSONAL STATEMENT

A highly motivated and experienced software engineering professional with strong communication, organisational, leadership and technical skills gained from several companies specialised in full-stack development, micro services, dependency injection, aspect oriented programming, database design and development, client server application with MVC design patterns, API engineering, DevOps and agile development process with more than six years of technical and managerial experience. Currently seeking to get a position as a Full stack Engineer in your company.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

# Senior Software Engineer

## 10/01/2019-08/14/2020

Ministry of innovation and technology mint.gov.et

- Develop Web portals for government institutions.
- Develop Government electronic services for all government institutions
- Consult on the country Digital Transformation Program strategies <u>eservices.gov.et</u> <u>Business or sector</u> Government institution

# Senior Software Developer

#### 10/01/2019-08/14/2020

Excellerent solutions www.excellerentsolutions.com

- Develop project management application for NGOs. <u>www.getmoyo.com</u>
- Develop custom dynamic reporting portal for Freight management system https://targetfmi.com/. Business or sector Consulting and IT services

company

#### Senior Software Developer

# 10/01/2019-08/14/2020

Apposit www.apposit.com

- Develop Rest API for POS APP.
- Give Customer Support and fix bugs on payment platform www.mypaga.com.
- Develop Backend for Digital Finance Module using Spring Framework.
- Integrating the platform to third party applications such as visa, master card and other payment platforms

• Creating unit tests.

Business or sector IT and Fin-tech industry

#### 05/27/2019-present

# Software Developer and Trainee

Gebeya www.gebeya.com

- Developing the backend using Node.js for a start up called mooyash.
- Take the role of a scrum master and product designer
- Creating unit tests

Business or sector Talent Market and Training centre

#### 03/12/2018-17/10/2019 Technical Manager

ITEX Technology Consulting www.yenante.co

- Manage the technical and business workflows.
- Prepare and present daily, weekly and monthly project progress reports and service performance reports.
- Troubleshoot and maintain SDP, IVR and other software and hardware systems.
- Setup new technical systems including servers, databases and network infrastructure.
- Communication with technical teams and clients to resolve issues or customisation requests.
- · Manages technical aspect of project delivery.
- Manages a team of 5 people from different functions.

Business or sector IT and Telecom Industry

#### 20/04/2015-09/11/2018

# Software Developer

ADC Research and Development www.adcethiopia.com

- Design and develop Industrial control applications.
- Propose and draft the development and implementation of best practice in industrial automation.
- Design and develop new network protocols and TCP/UDP communication modules for a newly designed hardware.
- Develop simulators for the control applications.
- Develop web applications for financial and enterprise solutions.
- Distribute tasks among team members and prepare project timeline.
- Follow up with the progress and ensure the project is completed on time.

Business or sector IT R&D

#### 30/12/2017-present

# Software Developer (Part-time)

Merita Technologies www.meritatech.com

- Develop, Test and fix bugs in web applications.
- Follow up with the client and ensure the project is completed with the client preference.
- Propose gamification ideas and their implementation for projects.

Business or sector IT and Telecom Industry

#### 1/11/2014-18/04/2015

# Software Developer and VAS Engineer

NWM Mobile Solutions www.nwmsolution.com

- · Configure sms gateways, databases and PHP scripts.
- Test, troubleshoot and maintain existing system and propose new features.
- Communicate with the telecom company team and ensure all the services are going smoothly.

Business or sector IT and Telecom Industry

# 14/03/2013-07/08/2013

# Intern Software Developer

Merita Technologies www.meritatech.com

- Design and develop web applications.
- Propose new ideas for development.
- Creating unit tests.
- Manual testing of soft wares.

Business or sector IT and Telecom Industry

#### **EDUCATION AND TRAINING**

### 01/09/2009-08/07/2014

# Bachelor of Science Computer Engineering

Addis Ababa Institute of technology, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

http://www.aait.edu.et/

# 05/27/2019-11/30/2019 Backend Engineering Specialisation

Gebeya Academy

https://www.gebeya.training/

PROJECTS INVOLVED IN	
	<ul> <li>File compressor using Huffman compression (Java).</li> <li>✓ Client: School Project</li> <li>✓ Description: File Compressor software for compressing files</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>✓ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product</li> <li>✓ Prepare test cases and test the system.</li> <li>✓ Optimise the software for maximum file compression.</li> </ul>
	<ul> <li>✦ Hotel Management System (ASP.net, MySQL).</li> <li>✓ Client: School Project</li> <li>✓ Description: A Hotel management system is used to manage the booking of hotel rooms.</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product</li> <li>➢ Prepare test cases and test the system.</li> <li>➢ Prepare a draft for feature development.</li> </ul>
	<ul> <li>❖ Finance management and Reporting System (CodeIgniter, PostgreSQL, HTML, jQuery, JavaScript).</li> <li>✓ Client: Lefayda Microfinance</li> <li>✓ Description: A Reporting module for comprehensive core banking module.</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➤ Writing stored procedures for reporting</li> <li>➤ Developing the frontend to display reports.</li> </ul>
	<ul> <li>❖ Grocery delivery system (Node.js, Android, MySQL, Loopback, Google Map API).</li> <li>✓ Client: X-Cog Technologies</li> <li>✓ Description: A Delivery system that connects Grocery Shops and costumers.</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product</li> <li>➢ Prepare test cases and test the system.</li> <li>➢ Prepare a draft for feature development.</li> </ul>
	<ul> <li>❖ IO Simulator for PLC (C++, Qt, C, Lua, python, SQLite).</li> <li>✓ Client: OMO Sugar Factory</li> <li>✓ Description: A input/output Simulator to test the automation of sugar factory</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product</li> <li>➢ Prepare test cases and test the system.</li> <li>➢ Enable the software to support multiple IO Modules.</li> </ul>
	<ul> <li>❖ SFC Editor for machine programming (C++, Qt, C, Lua, SQLite).</li> <li>✓ Client: OMO Sugar Factory</li> <li>✓ Description: A Software that generates code for automating machines by using graphical device.</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product</li> <li>➢ Prepare test cases and test the system</li> <li>➢ Giving bug fix support.</li> </ul>
	<ul> <li>❖ Serial Communication module for embedded processor (C++, Qt, C, Lua, python, Sqlite).</li> <li>✓ Client: OMO Sugar Factory.</li> <li>✓ Description: A Serial Communication module for industrial devices using Olimex MCC.</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➤ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product</li> <li>➤ Prepare test cases and test the system.</li> </ul>

*	Distributed Control System for sugar factory automation (C++, Qt, C, and Lua).  ✓ Client: OMO Sugar Factory.  ✓ Description: A Distributed Control System for one of the biggest factories in Ethiopia using Moxa IO Module.  ✓ Responsibilities  ➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product  ➢ Prepare test cases and test the system.  ➢ Optimise the software to support various failures  GIS Enabled Asset Management System (CodeIgniter, Map server, Openlayers, PostgreSQL).  ✓ Client: Horizon Express.  ✓ Description: A GIS Enables Asset Management System used to track items using locally developed hardware.  ✓ Responsibilities  ➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product  ➢ Prepare test cases and test the system.  ➢ Optimise the Open street map data and its rendering
*	<ul> <li>Mall Guide Mobile Application (Grails, MySQL).</li> <li>✓ Client: School Project.</li> <li>✓ Description: A Mall Guide and notification system fall malls in Addis.</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product</li> <li>➢ Prepare test cases and test the system.</li> </ul>
*	Online Training System (ASP.net, Microsoft SQL Server).  ✓ Client: OTIS Elevator  ✓ Description: A Gamified Training system for Sales personnel.  ✓ Responsibilities  ➤ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product  ➤ Prepare test cases and test the system.
*	Human resource information system (CodeIgniter Framework, PostgreSQL).  ✓ Client: Tracon Trading ✓ Description: A Human Resource management system.  ✓ Responsibilities ➤ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product ➤ Prepare test cases and test the system.
*	School Management System (CodeIgniter Framework PostgreSQL).  ✓ Client: Nejashi School  ✓ Description: A School Management system and connects the teachers with the parents  ✓ Responsibilities  ➤ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product  ➤ Prepare test cases and test the system.
*	SMS Management System (Laravel Framework, Maria DB).  ✓ Client: Zokida Consult.  ✓ Description: A SMS Management system to send bulk sms and receive from clients.  ✓ Responsibilities  ➤ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product  ➤ Prepare test cases and test the system.
*	Recipe Management and E-Commerce System (React, Node.js, Mongo dB).  ✓ Client: Mooyash Plc.  ✓ Description: A Mobile Application for live cooking and recipe management.  ✓ Responsibilities  ➢ Requirement Analysis design and development of the product  ➢ Prepare test cases and test the system.  ➢ Develop the idea and draft new features.

*	Payment Platform and Digital Finance System (Spring Framework, MySQL Server, PostgreSQL Mongodb).  ✓ Client: Pagatech.  ✓ Description: A Payment platform that is implemented in Nigeria and has more than 16 million active users.  ✓ Responsibilities  ➤ Giving Bug fix and support for the clients.  ➤ Develop new APIs and integration with other platforms
*	<ul> <li>Project management tool for fundraisers and NGOS (asp.net core, Angular)</li> <li>✓ Client: Moyo.</li> <li>✓ Description: A project management tool that helps fundraisers to plan and manage their projects from imagination to implementation phases</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➤ Giving Bug fix and support for the clients.</li> <li>➤ Develop features.</li> </ul>
*	<ul> <li>Dynamic Reporting tool for Freight management (.React, PHP)</li> <li>✓ Client: Moyo.</li> <li>✓ Description: A dynamic reporting tool for customers and admins to generate a dynamic report for multiple datasets.</li> <li>✓ Responsibilities</li> <li>➤ Develop new features.</li> </ul>
*	Online Gallery, Dynamic website and Directory portal (React.js, Node.js, Mongodb)  ✓ Client: Ministry of Culture and tourism.  ✓ Description: three government portals for archiving images ,dynamic interactive website and Government directory portal  ✓ Responsibilities  ➤ Develop new features.

# PROGRAMMING SKILLS

- ❖ Object Oriented Programming C++, Java, JavaScript ,C#
- **Embedded Programming** C, Python, Lua
- Backend PHP, .NET Core, CodeIgniter, Laravel, Map Server, Node.js/Express/loopback, Spring MVC, Spring Boot and Spring Core
- Frontend HTML, JavaScript, Jquery, React.js, Openlayers, Angular
- Database PostgreSQL, MySQL, Mongo dB, Microsoft SQL Server, Maria DB
- ❖ Frameworks Documentation Tools Swagger, API Doc, Spring Rest Doc
- ❖ Version control tools Git, SVN
- Methodologies Agile, Scrum, Waterfall.
- ❖ Web and application servers Apache, Tomcat, Nginx
- DevOps Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes
- SMS Gateway tools Kannel, OzekiSMS

#### SOFTWARE PROFICIENCY SKILLS

Code-blocks for C++, IAR for C, Eclipse for Java, Android Studio for Android, IntelXDK for mobile app, MATLAB for analysis and data visualisation, Qt for C++, Inkscape and Gimp for graphics editing, GitLab and RapidSVN version control system, Microsoft Office, Postman.

# DevOps SKILLS

\* AWS, Scheduled systems, Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes and shell scripting.

# OPERATING SYSTEM PROFICIENCY SKILLS

Windows, Ubuntu, Debian and kali Linux with command line expertise.

#### PERSONAL SKILLS

# Mother tongue Amharic

Ot	her l	lang	gua	ge

English

Arabic

UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING			
Listening	Reading	Spoken interaction	Spoken production				
Proficient	Proficient	Proficient	Proficient	Proficient			
IELTS Certification awarded with over all band score of 6.5							
Basic	Basic	Basic	Basic	Basic			
No International certification awarded							

Communication skills

Good communication skills gained through my experience as software developer

Organisational / managerial skills

Good leadership and organisational skills gained as a team leader in company projects and in managerial positions.

Job-related skills

Fast learning skills, adaptability with new technologies and perseverance to work.

# REFERENCES

- Mr Fitsum Assaminew
- Instructor at Addis Ababa institute of technology
  - Addis Ababa, Ethiopia
    - <u>fitsum.assamnew@aait.edu.et</u>
- Mr Howard James
- CEO at Merita Technologies
- Nairobi, Kenya
  - howardjames.mail@gmail.com